<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pandora, the musyque of the beautie, of his mistresse Diana. Composed by Iohn Soowthern Gentleman, and dedicated to the right Honorable, Edward Deuer, Earle of Oxenford, &amp;c. 1584. Iune. 20</title>
            <author>Southern, John, fl. 1584.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111056</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846479</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 354:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pandora, the musyque of the beautie, of his mistresse Diana. Composed by Iohn Soowthern Gentleman, and dedicated to the right Honorable, Edward Deuer, Earle of Oxenford, &amp;c. 1584. Iune. 20</title>
                  <author>Southern, John, fl. 1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By John Charlewood] for Thomas Hackette, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Lumbert streete, vnder the Popes head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Includes "Foure epytaphes, made by the Countes of Oxenford, after the death of her young sonne, the Lord Bulbecke, &amp;c." and "Epitaph, made by the Queenes Maiestie, at the death of the Princesse of Espinoye".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:1"/>
            <p>PANDORA, The Muſyque of the beautie of his Miſtreſſe <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Compoſed by <hi>John Soowthern</hi> Gentleman, and dedicated to the right <hi>Honorable,</hi> Edward Deuer, <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Oxenford. &amp;c.</hi> 1584. Iune. 20.</p>
            <q>Non careo patria, Me caret Illa magis.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Jmprinted at London for <hi>Thomas Hackette,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe in Lumbert ſtreete, vnder the Popes head. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="ode">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:2"/>
            <head>To the ryght honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Earle of Oxenford. &amp;c. <hi>Ode.</hi> 1.</head>
            <lg n="1" type="strophe">
               <head>
                  <hi>Strophe.</hi> 1.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His earth, is the nouriſhing teate,</l>
               <l>As well that deliuers to eate:</l>
               <l>As els throwes out all that we can</l>
               <l>Deuiſe, that ſhould be naedefull fore</l>
               <l>The health, of or diſeaſe or ſore,</l>
               <l>The houſhold companions of man.</l>
               <l>And this earth, hath hearbes ſoueraine,</l>
               <l>To empeach ſickneſſes ſodaine,</l>
               <l>If they be well aptlie applide.</l>
               <l>And this yearth, ſpues vp many a breuage,</l>
               <l>Of which if we knew well the vſage:</l>
               <l>Would force the force <hi>Acherontide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bréefe, it lendes vs all that we haue,</l>
               <l>With to liue: and it is our graue.</l>
               <l>But with all this, yet cannot giue,</l>
               <l>Vs fayre renowmes, when we be dead.</l>
               <l>And in déede they are onelie made,</l>
               <l>By our owne vertues whiles we liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="antistrophe">
               <head>Antiſtrophe.</head>
               <l>¶ And Marbles (all be they ſo ſtrong,)</l>
               <l>Cannot maintaine our renowmes long:</l>
               <l>And neither they he but abuſes,</l>
               <l>To thinke that other thinges haue puiſſaunce,</l>
               <l>To make for time any reſiſtaunce,</l>
               <l>Saue onelie the well ſinging <hi>Muſes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the fayre <hi>Muſes</hi> that prouide,</l>
               <l>For the wiſe, an immortall name:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:3"/>
               <l>Doo neuer garniſhe any head.</l>
               <l>With Lawrell, by heareſay of Fame.</l>
               <l>Nor euerie one that can rime,</l>
               <l>Muſt not thinke to triumph on time.</l>
               <l>For they giue not their Diuine furie,</l>
               <l>To euerie doting troupe that comes.</l>
               <l>Nor the touch of eu'rie ones thommes,</l>
               <l>Is not of an eternall durie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="epode">
               <head>Epode.</head>
               <l>¶ No, no, the high ſinger is hée</l>
               <l>Alone: that in the ende muſt bée</l>
               <l>Made proude, with a garland lyke this,</l>
               <l>And not eu'rie ryming nouice,</l>
               <l>That writes with ſmall wit, and much paine:</l>
               <l>And the (Gods knowe) idiot in vaine,</l>
               <l>For it's not the way to <hi>Parnaſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor it wyll neither come to paſſe,</l>
               <l>If it be not in ſome wiſe fiction,</l>
               <l>And of an ingenious inuenſion:</l>
               <l>And infanted with pleaſant trauaill,</l>
               <l>For it alone muſt win the Laurell.</l>
               <l>And onelie the Poet well borne,</l>
               <l>Muſt be he that goes to <hi>Parnaſſus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And not theſe companies of Aſſes,</l>
               <l>That haue brought verce almoſt to ſcorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2" type="strophe">
               <head>Strophe. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>¶ Making ſpeake (her with a ſwéete brute)</l>
               <l>The ten diuers tongues of my Lute,</l>
               <l>I will <hi>Fredone</hi> in thy honour,</l>
               <l>Theſe renowmed ſongs of <hi>Pindar:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And immitate for thée <hi>Deuer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horace,</hi> that braue Latine Harper.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:3"/>
               <l>And ſtand vp Nymphes <hi>Aganapide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Stand vp my wantons <hi>Parnaſside,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Stand vp wantons and that we ſing,</l>
               <l>A newe dittie <hi>Calaborois,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To the <hi>Iban</hi> harpe <hi>Thebanois,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That had ſuch a murmuring ſtring.</l>
               <l>For I will ſhewt, héere with my verees,</l>
               <l>(Following the auncient traces)</l>
               <l>As high vp to the ayre this Hymne,</l>
               <l>(With a ſtrong bowe and armes, preſumpſtous)</l>
               <l>As <hi>Deuer</hi> is both wiſe and vertuous,</l>
               <l>And as of my Harpe, he is digne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="antistrophe">
               <head>Antiſtrophe.</head>
               <l>¶<hi>Muſes,</hi> you haue had of your father,</l>
               <l>Onelie, the particuler fauer,</l>
               <l>To kéepe fro the réeue enfernall:</l>
               <l>And therefore my wantons come ſing,</l>
               <l>Vpon your moſt beſt ſpeaking ſtring,</l>
               <l>His name that dooth chéeriſhe you all.</l>
               <l>Come Nimphes while I haue a deſire,</l>
               <l>To ſtrike on a well ſounding <hi>Lyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of our vertues <hi>Deuer</hi> the name.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deuer,</hi> that had giuen him in parte:</l>
               <l>The Loue, the Warre, Honour, and Arte,</l>
               <l>And with them an eternall Fame.</l>
               <l>Come Nimphes, your puiſſaunce is diuine:</l>
               <l>And to thoſe that you ſhew no fauour;</l>
               <l>Quicklie they are depriude of honour,</l>
               <l>And ſlaues to the chaines <hi>Coſsitine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="epode">
               <head>Epode,</head>
               <l>¶ Amongſt our well renowmed men,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deuer</hi> merits a ſyluer pen,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:4"/>
               <l>Eternally to write his honour,</l>
               <l>And I in a well poliſht verſe,</l>
               <l>Can ſet vp in our Vniuerſe,</l>
               <l>A Fame, to endure for euer.</l>
               <l>And fylde with a <hi>Furiae</hi> extreme;</l>
               <l>Vpon a well ſuperbus ryme:</l>
               <l>(On a ryme, and both ſtrong and true)</l>
               <l>I wyll <hi>(Deuer)</hi> puſhe thy louanges,</l>
               <l>To the eares of people eſtraunges:</l>
               <l>And rauiſhe them with thy vertus.</l>
               <l>But in trueth I vſe but to ſing,</l>
               <l>After the well intuned ſtring,</l>
               <l>Of eyether of the great <hi>Prophêts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>Thebain,</hi> or <hi>Calaborois:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of whether of whome yet the voice,</l>
               <l>Hath not béene knowne to our <hi>Poëts.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3" type="strophe">
               <head>Strophe. 3.</head>
               <l>¶ But what ſhall I beginne to touch:</l>
               <l>O <hi>Muſes</hi> what haue I begunne,</l>
               <l>But ſpeake wantons, what haue I donne:</l>
               <l>Take it of the charge is too much.</l>
               <l>No, no, if I would there were made,</l>
               <l>I could take an entyre <hi>Iliade,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of onelie his noble antiquitie.</l>
               <l>But his vertues would bluſhe with ſhame:</l>
               <l>If I ſhould not by his owne name,</l>
               <l>Giue him a laude to our poſteritie.</l>
               <l>But if I will thus like <hi>Pindar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In many diſcourſes <hi>Egar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before I wyll come to my point:</l>
               <l>Or, or touch his infinitie</l>
               <l>Of vertues, in this <hi>Poieſie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our ſong wyll neuer be conioint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="antistrophe">
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:4"/>
               <head>Antiſtrophe.</head>
               <l>¶ For who marketh better then hée,</l>
               <l>The ſeuen turning flames of the Skie:</l>
               <l>Or hath read more of the antique.</l>
               <l>Hath greater knowledge in the tongues:</l>
               <l>Or vnderſtandes ſooner the ſownes,</l>
               <l>Of the learner to loue Muſique.</l>
               <l>Or elſe who hath a fayrer grace,</l>
               <l>In the <hi>Centauriane</hi> arte of <hi>Thrace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Halfe-horſe, halfe-man, and with leſſe paine,</l>
               <l>Dooth bring the Coorſſer, indomtable,</l>
               <l>To yéeld to the raynes of his bridle;</l>
               <l>Vaulting, on the edge of a plaine.</l>
               <l>And it pleaſes me to ſaye too,</l>
               <l>(With a louange, I proteſt true)</l>
               <l>That in England we cannot ſées,</l>
               <l>Any thing lyke <hi>Deuer,</hi> but hée.</l>
               <l>Onelie himſelfe he muſt reſemble,</l>
               <l>Vertues ſo much in him aſſemble.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="epode">
               <head>Epode.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ And nought eſcapes out of my hand,</l>
                  <l>In this <hi>Ode,</hi> but it's veritée:</l>
                  <l>And héere I ſweare <hi>Deuer</hi> tis thée,</l>
                  <l>That art ornament of England.</l>
                  <l>Vaunting me againe of this thing:</l>
                  <l>Which is, that I ſhall neuer ſing,</l>
                  <l>A man ſo much honoured as thée,</l>
                  <l>And both of the <hi>Muſes</hi> and mée.</l>
                  <l>And when I gette the ſpoyle of <hi>Thebes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hauing charged it on my ſhoulders.</l>
                  <l>In verſes exempte fro the webbes,</l>
                  <l>Of the ruinous <hi>Filandinge</hi> ſyſters:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11450:5"/>
                  <l>I promiſe to bullde thée a glorie,</l>
                  <l>That ſhall euer line in memorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ In meane while, take this lyttle thing:</l>
                  <l>But as ſmall as it is: <hi>Deuere.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vaunt vs that neuer man before,</l>
                  <l>Now in England, knewe <hi>Pindars</hi> ſtring.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Non car<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> patria, Me caret Illa magi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <head>Sonnet to the Reader.</head>
            <l>THou find'ſt not heere, neither the furious alarmes,</l>
            <l>Of the pride of <hi>Spaine,</hi> or ſubtilnes of <hi>France:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor of the rude Engliſh, or mutine <hi>Almanes:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor neither of <hi>Naples,</hi> noble men of armes.</l>
            <l>No, an Infant, and that yet ſurmounteth Knights:</l>
            <l>Hath both vanquiſhed me, and alſo my Muſe.</l>
            <l>And vvere it not: this is a lawfull excuſe.</l>
            <l>If thou hearſt not the report, of their great fights,</l>
            <l>Thou ſhalt ſee no death of any valliant ſoldier,</l>
            <l>And yet I ſing the beauty of a fierce vvarrier.</l>
            <l>And amore alone I muſt ſtrike on my <hi>Leer,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And but <hi>Eroto</hi> I knowe no other Muſe.</l>
            <l>And harke all you that are lyke vs amourous.</l>
            <l>And you that are not, goe read ſome other where.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sonnets">
            <div n="1" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnets. 1. <hi>To his Myſtreſſe</hi> Diana.</head>
               <l>TIs fyrſt to you <hi>Dian,</hi> that I haue togethers,</l>
               <l>Giuen me and my voice, making you the <hi>Idôll:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To which I offer both the body and ſoule,</l>
               <l>Of theſe teares of my eyes, that fall héere like riuers.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:5"/>
               <l>But in ſome thinges fabelons, you muſt be content</l>
               <l>To ſee what it is, of vs Louers the flame,</l>
               <l>And reade you muſt vnder a Goddeſſes name,</l>
               <l>Of your beates the delycate ornament.</l>
               <l>And where as theſe which are to apayſe your cruelties:</l>
               <l>Shall not proſcribe well, your excellent rareties.</l>
               <l>Excuſe mee Nymphe, as you would haue in ſome <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te.</l>
               <l>Of heauen your fayre ſemblance: for I doo not meane,</l>
               <l>To ſing you now: but <hi>Dian,</hi> when you haue bene,</l>
               <l>More gratious vnto mée: I wyll ſing you better.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 2.</head>
               <l>THe Gréeke Poet, to whome <hi>Bathill</hi> was the guide,</l>
               <l>Made her immortall, by that which he did ſing:</l>
               <l>And (were it ſo I knowe not but) of <hi>Corîne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We faine the patrone of the Latine <hi>Ouide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſince them <hi>(Petrarque)</hi> a wiſe <hi>Florentîne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath turnde his Miſtres into a tree of Baye.</l>
               <l>And he that ſoong the eldeſt daughter of <hi>Troye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Fraunce</hi> hath made of her, an aſtre Diuine.</l>
               <l>And lyke theſe knowne men, can your <hi>Soothern,</hi> write too:</l>
               <l>And as long as <hi>Engliſhe</hi> laſts, immortall you.</l>
               <l>I the penne of <hi>Soothern</hi> will my ſayre <hi>Diana,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Make thée immortall: if thou wilt giue him fauour:</l>
               <l>For then hée'll ſing <hi>Petrark, Tîen, Ouide, Ronſar:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And make thee <hi>Caſſander, Corine, Bathyll, Laura.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 3.</head>
               <l>THat death that deſpiſes at all kinde of beautie.</l>
               <l>And would make all loue, goe into <hi>Charons</hi> paſſage:</l>
               <l>Would haue hit the eyes, wherein I liue in ſeruage:</l>
               <l>The eyes both to fayre, and too full of crueltie.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Cupid</hi> that ſtyll in thoſe eyes was indompted:</l>
               <l>The infant knew well, where after this death ſought:</l>
               <l>And began to crie (death) if thou ende thy thought,</l>
               <l>We ſhall neither of vs, be againe redoubted.</l>
               <l>But (death) if thout let me liue in theſe eyes ſtyll:</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt ſée (O then) how nobelly I wyll.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:6"/>
               <l>Hoyſe thy honour? for I haue not halfe thy might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And yet in theſe eyes, I conquer all the world:</l>
               <l>Death hearing this, let him line ſtyll in the ſyght:</l>
               <l>Fro whence he ſhewteth ſuch ſharpe arrowes of gold.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 4.</head>
               <l>WHen nature made my <hi>Diana,</hi> that before</l>
               <l>All other <hi>Nymphes:</hi> ſhowld force the hearts rebell<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt:</l>
               <l>She gaue her the maſſe, of beauties excellent,</l>
               <l>That ſhe kéepe ſince long, in her coffers in ſtore.</l>
               <l>And at her framing, <hi>Paphae</hi> came fro the ſkies,</l>
               <l>with the ſwéetnes, and graces, of <hi>Erycêene:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſwore that it ſhould make her ſo fayre <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Quéene,</l>
               <l>Of beautie: that the Gods ſhould dwell in her eyes.</l>
               <l>But ſhe hardlie was come to vs. fro aboue:</l>
               <l>Though? but my ſoule was inflamed with her loue.</l>
               <l>And I ſerue her in ſpite of the troupe <hi>Celêſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For tell mee? why did not they lykewiſe ordaine:</l>
               <l>That in reward of my loue, ſhe ſhewd againe,</l>
               <l>Eſtéeme me onely, and onely, loue me beſt.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 5.</head>
               <l>OF ſtars, and of forreſts, <hi>Dian.</hi> is the honor:</l>
               <l>And to the ſeas, to the Goddeſſe, is the guide:</l>
               <l>And ſhe hath <hi>Luna, Charon,</hi> and <hi>Eumenîde:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make brightnes, to giue death, and to cauſe horror.</l>
               <l>And my warrier, my light, ſhines in thy fayre eyes:</l>
               <l>My dread is of thée, the to great excellence:</l>
               <l>Thy wordes kyll mee: and thus thou haſt the puiſſaunce,</l>
               <l>Of her that rules the ſlodes, and lyghines the ſkies.</l>
               <l>And as ſyluer <hi>Pheb,</hi> is the after, moſt clare:</l>
               <l>So is thy beauty, the beauty, the moſt rare.</l>
               <l>Wherefore I call thée <hi>Dian,</hi> for thy beantee,</l>
               <l>For thy wiſedome, and for thy puiſſannce Celeſt.</l>
               <l>And yet thou muſt be but a Goddeſſe tereſt:</l>
               <l>And onely becauſe of thy great crueltée.</l>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:6"/>
            <div n="6" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 6.</head>
               <l>OF <hi>Pyladeus,</hi> and of <hi>Oreſteus,</hi> we haue</l>
               <l>made many diſputes, in the temple of death:</l>
               <l>And in the Church of <hi>Troy,</hi> we pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue <hi>Choreb's</hi> faith,</l>
               <l>Who made for <hi>Caſſander,</hi> his h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, his graue.</l>
               <l>And there is one, on the mountaine <hi>Cancaſein,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With an Eagle, on his heart <hi>Philoſiphâll.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And there is a ſtone of a mad <hi>Ciſyphâll,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leaſt alwayes behind him, and caried in vaine.</l>
               <l>Theſe temples, and this rocke, is in my obiect:</l>
               <l>The church is my ſoule, the ſlint is my ſubiect.</l>
               <l>My verſes are the labours of <hi>Siſyphêus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And for willing ſhew your fayre beauties, its vaine.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Promet,</hi> for not canning. I haue the paine:</l>
               <l>Th'Eagle's cruell, and <hi>(Nymphe)</hi> you are rigrous.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 7.</head>
               <l>I Am not (my, cruell warrier) the <hi>Thebain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That my infancie, ſhould be ſtrangled with Serpents:</l>
               <l>Nor neither did my nurſe giue thée any torments:</l>
               <l>nor I ſuckt neither <hi>Vropae,</hi> nor <hi>Elthâin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I came not (my warrier) of the blood <hi>Lidain:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor neyther am I of the race, of <hi>Ixiôn:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Ioue,</hi> neither bare my mother, affection:</l>
               <l>Nor I am no infant <hi>Egier,</hi> nor <hi>Danain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor I am neither the nephew of <hi>Atlas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That made the earth dronke, with the blood of <hi>Arguſſ:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But yet I know wherefore I haue all my wounds.</l>
               <l>I am none of theſe which I haue ſayd <hi>(Diân)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But I am that verie miſerable man,</l>
               <l>Who for regarding thée, was eaten of Houndes.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="elegies">
            <div n="1" type="elegy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegia. 1.</hi> To the Echon.</head>
               <l>O Dolefull voice, that dooſt aunſwer,</l>
               <l>The wéepings of my care:</l>
               <l>And that héere in theſe mozie groues,</l>
               <l>Haſt pittie on my dolanc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:7"/>
               <l>And th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of whome ſhe emptie mouth,</l>
               <l>(At leaſt) dooth make a ſemblaunce,</l>
               <l>To ſéele my wounds that procéede of</l>
               <l>Two eyes, to gréene, and fayre.</l>
               <l>O ſpeake ſince thou canſt not liue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</l>
               <l>I ſhall giue the brethe:</l>
               <l>And ſince my gréeuous voice, is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</l>
               <l>the nurce of thy ſteme:</l>
               <l>I crying <hi>Dian,</hi> why makeſt thou</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dye Iohn,</hi> aunſwer agen:</l>
               <l>Wouldſt thou I lou'de no more,</l>
               <l>Or dooſt thou Propheſie my death.</l>
               <l>O noble Nymph tell mée, or dooſt</l>
               <l>Thou now inflame againe,</l>
               <l>With the antiqueus amor, that</l>
               <l>Thou louedſt ſo in vaine.</l>
               <l>Or is it that remembring my</l>
               <l>Loue, I ſhould pittie thine.</l>
               <l>For the like dollor that thou hadſt,</l>
               <l>Euen the like doo I ſuffer:</l>
               <l>And the like amore that thou hadſt,</l>
               <l>The like to mee dooth offer:</l>
               <l>Saue that thy loue was not ſo fayre,</l>
               <l>Nor ſo cruelly as mine.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="elegy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegia. 2.</hi> To the Gods.</head>
               <l>WHen the eye of the world dooth waſhe,</l>
               <l>his golden ſhining heaire,</l>
               <l>In the large Occean ſeas: and that</l>
               <l>They haue couerd the lyght:</l>
               <l>Amurmuring repoſe, and a</l>
               <l>Reſtfull and ſléepy night,</l>
               <l>Is ſpreded both ouer the earth,</l>
               <l>The waters and the ayre.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:7"/>
               <l>But I chaunge nature then? For than,</l>
               <l>Dooth my brighteſt <hi>Aurôr,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In a ſwéete dreame preſent her ſelfe,</l>
               <l>O dreame, no dreame: but well,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Ambrozie,</hi> the <hi>Nectar,</hi> and</l>
               <l>The <hi>Manna,</hi> Eternell.</l>
               <l>And to be bréefe, a viſion that</l>
               <l>I lyke a God adore.</l>
               <l>Wherefore farewell, day of nights, and</l>
               <l>Welcome night waking daye:</l>
               <l>And farewell waking, of my ſléepe,</l>
               <l>Welcome ſléepe, lyuing ioye.</l>
               <l>But what ſay I, my wealth is falſe,</l>
               <l>And my euill verita-ble:</l>
               <l>And I plaine of them both, for I</l>
               <l>Haue in neither delight:</l>
               <l>Except ye Gods will ſhort theſe dayes,</l>
               <l>And eterniſhe this night:</l>
               <l>An<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that God that will doo it, ſhall</l>
               <l>be a God charita-ble.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="elegy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegia. 3.</hi> To his Diana.</head>
               <l>IF the ſecretneſſe of my thoughtes,</l>
               <l>Were opened to you,</l>
               <l>Or if elſe my dolorous heart,</l>
               <l>Had of ſpeaking the vſage:</l>
               <l>Or (warrier) if my conſtancie,</l>
               <l>Were painted in my viſage:</l>
               <l>Or that if ye knewe my torment,</l>
               <l>How it is great and true.</l>
               <l>Or, or if any golden wordes,</l>
               <l>In well compoſed verſe,</l>
               <l>Could liuelelie ſhewe the picture,</l>
               <l>Of an amourous rage:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:8"/>
               <l>Then ſhould I without doubt amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe</l>
               <l>a <hi>Tigers</hi> courage.</l>
               <l>And moue to pittie (warrier) if</l>
               <l>it were the vniuerce.</l>
               <l>But ſince wordes, neither can preſcribe</l>
               <l>My amore, nor my paine:</l>
               <l>Tyme ſhall it ſelfe, witneſſe how much</l>
               <l>Both are in me certaine:</l>
               <l>And that of my paſſioned ſoule,</l>
               <l>The Diuine great loyalties:</l>
               <l>Doo the ſacredneſſe of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</l>
               <l>I of the Gods paſſe:</l>
               <l>And more then the ſyluer maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties,</l>
               <l>of your Chriſtall face,</l>
               <l>Vnderneath, tother <hi>Phebes,</hi> doo</l>
               <l>Excell all other <hi>Beutaes.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnets">
            <div n="8" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 8.</head>
               <l>THough I wiſh to haue your fauour, which is ſuch,</l>
               <l>That it is but for Gods, thinke you my <hi>Audâce,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like his that in your ſtéede, dyd a clowde imbrace:</l>
               <l>Or his that was a harte, by ſeéing ſo much.</l>
               <l>Or would you elſe becauſe of my hautaine thought,</l>
               <l>That I might augment the Sepulchres of <hi>Thrace:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or that I were as the giant <hi>Briarâs:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or paide lyke the wagoner ſo euelie taught.</l>
               <l>No? lybertie, <hi>Rome,</hi> thy wrath the ſeas <hi>(Diân)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Grée<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>Pirats?</hi> thy merie Muſt ſaue <hi>Ariôn.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or if thou wylt none of theſe aforeſayde thinges:</l>
               <l>Becauſe thou ſayſt that my mindes are ſet ſo high,</l>
               <l>If thou thinkſt I beginne lyke <hi>Icâr</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lie:</l>
               <l>Since th'eyes are my ſonne, let thy loue be my winges.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnets. 9.</head>
               <l>IT is after our deathes, a thing mani-feſt.</l>
               <l>we bothe goe to hell, and ſuffer helliſhe paines:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:8"/>
               <l>you, for your rigour, I, for my thoughts haultaines,</l>
               <l>That attempt to loue a Goddeſſe ſo Celeſt.</l>
               <l>But as for mee I ſhall be lyttle afflicted,</l>
               <l>Tis you (my warrier) that muſt haue the torment:</l>
               <l>For I that but, in ſéeing you am content:</l>
               <l>you, with mée, I'll bleſſe the place ſo much deteſted.</l>
               <l>And my ſoule that is raued with your fayre eyes,</l>
               <l>In the midſt of hell, wyll eſtabliſhe, a ſkeyes:</l>
               <l>Making my bright day, in the eternall night.</l>
               <l>And when all the damned elſe are in annoy:</l>
               <l>I'll ſmyle in that glorie, ſéeing you my ioy:</l>
               <l>And being once there, goe not out of our ſight.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 10.</head>
               <l>THe heauens willing ſhew fauour among our paines.</l>
               <l>And to make both runne, of my wéeping the ſtreame:</l>
               <l>And alſo eternall, your rigor extreame:</l>
               <l>turnd your heart, to rocke, and my eyes to fountaynes:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Cupid</hi> dooth bache him in my ſyluer ryuers:</l>
               <l>And being come out, of the flodes, of my yll:</l>
               <l>He flies to your rocke, where as vpon a hyll,</l>
               <l>The lyttle wanton, dooth prime, and rowſe his feathers.</l>
               <l>But when thy winter comes, and that thou art olde,</l>
               <l>Felling thy rocke-hart, vnder his tallons colde:</l>
               <l>Hée'll byd thee adiew with an eternall farewell.</l>
               <l>And then thou haſt fayre to ſay Loue is a rage:</l>
               <l>Olde folke ſay ſo, cauſe <hi>Cupid</hi> dooth abhorre age:</l>
               <l>But were they lou'de then, I doubt th'ed not be cruell.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="elegies">
            <div n="4" type="elegy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegia. 4.</hi> To the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CVpid</hi> hath ſwelde my ſtomacke, with</l>
               <l>On ſuch a ſacred poyſon,</l>
               <l>And I am in Quéene <hi>Venus</hi> fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</l>
               <l>ſo well entertained:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:9"/>
               <l>That lyke a captiue, languiſhing,</l>
               <l>And with dolour, tormented,</l>
               <l>I thinke my ſelfe well happy, to</l>
               <l>Be in a Womans priſon.</l>
               <l>Now? As for you wretches that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</l>
               <l>but yrons can puniſhe,</l>
               <l>If you lyſt you may haue a hope,</l>
               <l>to be at lyber-tie:</l>
               <l>But as for mée? I tell you, I'll</l>
               <l>die in captiui-tie:</l>
               <l>Conſuming héere in the quicke-ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-fayre-eyes</l>
               <l>of my Goddeſſe,</l>
               <l>And well I am contented in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede,</l>
               <l>with her extréeme rigore.</l>
               <l>Swearing, that I neuer fell in</l>
               <l>My ſoule ſo great a dolore,</l>
               <l>As when I thinke for her likewiſe,</l>
               <l>Some other ſhould haue paſſion.</l>
               <l>And with all this too, yet I haue</l>
               <l>Neither loſt all my iudgement:</l>
               <l>For we ſaye that man is happy,</l>
               <l>onelie, that is well content,</l>
               <l>And I tell you, (you wretches) it</l>
               <l>is all my contentation.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="elegy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Elegia. 5.</hi> To his thoughts.</head>
               <l>MY thoughts, to full of thought, to thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</l>
               <l>thoughts giue now? Repoſe,</l>
               <l>Both to my dolefull ſoule, and to</l>
               <l>my hope that is in vaine:</l>
               <l>For well though my teares drop, fro my</l>
               <l>eyes like a ſwift fountaine?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:9"/>
               <l>Murmuring my <hi>Alas:</hi> ſhe hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</l>
               <l>not to my propoſe.</l>
               <l>My thoughts, too full of thought, and too</l>
               <l>Farre engrau'n in my heart.</l>
               <l>My thoughts too full of thought, that giue</l>
               <l>mée ouer to my dolore:</l>
               <l>My thoughts too thoughtfull, if you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</l>
               <l>yet any more langore:</l>
               <l>My thought full thoughts, (O Gods) doo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce</l>
               <l>therewithall my mort.</l>
               <l>And Opinaſtres thoughts the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</l>
               <l>of my extréeme paines.</l>
               <l>And thoughts that boyle this ſulfer hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor</l>
               <l>in my drooping vaines.</l>
               <l>Speake thoughtfull thoughts, why féede you me</l>
               <l>With this <hi>Abiſt</hi> eſperaunce.</l>
               <l>When poſſeſſing the ioye, of which</l>
               <l>I haue had ſuch deſyres:</l>
               <l>And for Idolling the fayre eyes,</l>
               <l>In which are my plaſyres:</l>
               <l>In the end thoughtes, for reward thought</l>
               <l>Dooth bréede mée a repentaunce.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="elegy">
               <head>Elegia. 6. <hi>To his</hi> Diana.</head>
               <l>MY hope dooth fell mée, that after</l>
               <l>This great rigour, of you:</l>
               <l>I ſhall with ſacred guerdons,</l>
               <l>Be recom-penſed for wrong:</l>
               <l>Shewing mée that I merite it,</l>
               <l>Being patience ſo long.</l>
               <l>But this imagind hope, (my cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</l>
               <l>warrier) is it true,</l>
               <l>My hope dooth tell mée too <hi>(Diana)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That your Diuine beau-tie,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:10"/>
               <l>Cannot be accompanied with</l>
               <l>Such crueltie as thine.</l>
               <l>But what is't (my angrie warrier)</l>
               <l>That yéeldes this plague of mine:</l>
               <l>Fortune? or the origene of</l>
               <l>The cauſe of cru-eltie.</l>
               <l>My hope dooth tell mée too (my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier)</l>
               <l>that my dolefull langore:</l>
               <l>Will in a paſſient ende, amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe</l>
               <l>your extréeme great rigore:</l>
               <l>The which all if it can, when your</l>
               <l>Mothers gone we ſhall trie,</l>
               <l>But if it cannot doo it then,</l>
               <l>But would yet féede mée ſtyll,</l>
               <l>With preſſes of time: I'll giue ou'r:</l>
               <l>And eu'r after I will,</l>
               <l>Eſtéeme our Fortune, too much lowe,</l>
               <l>For a hope ſet ſo high.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnets">
            <div n="11" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnet. 11.</head>
               <l>HE that was the firſt, that put theſe lyttle winges,</l>
               <l>On the backe of a more, that high God immortell:</l>
               <l>He might better haue had employed his penſell,</l>
               <l>To paint hopping butter-flyes, or Genny wrens.</l>
               <l>But if in place of them, the doting foole had</l>
               <l>Painted his fierce howe, and his rigorous draftes,</l>
               <l>And ſhewde what kinde of thinges, are his golden ſhaftes:</l>
               <l>Then had he béene apt to haue painted a God.</l>
               <l>And you that paint next, you muſt vſe other colore:</l>
               <l>wherewith you may better ſhew his diuine rigore:</l>
               <l>And for his bowe, giue him a great harquebous.</l>
               <l>Or beléeue you not, goe and looke on <hi>Diân,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And hauing ſeéne her fayre eyes. I eſtée me than,</l>
               <l>you'll giue him ſome thing more then it rigorous.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:10"/>
               <head>Sonnet. 12.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>AEnêas, Orphêus, Cephall,</hi> and <hi>Demophôn:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pocris,</hi> of <hi>Eurydice, Phyllis,</hi> and <hi>Creuſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Haue made complaintes, as they haue béene amorous,</l>
               <l>Saying, theyr miſtreſſes, did doo them all wrong,</l>
               <l>Though they themſelues to theyr loues, did all amiſſe.</l>
               <l>For one gaue <hi>Phyllis,</hi> a poore mournefull ſe-quell,</l>
               <l>And th'other, left <hi>Procris,</hi> in the vall's of hell,</l>
               <l>And with t'others fault, di-ed <hi>Euridice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aenêas,</hi> the laſt was thought to haue leaſt fault.</l>
               <l>Though the preſumpſion is yet great for all that.</l>
               <l>But <hi>(Dian)</hi> you knoe <hi>(Dian)</hi> your amourous,</l>
               <l>Hath not learned lyke any of them <hi>Protê.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though you are <hi>Demoph, Cephall, Orpheus, Aenê:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And he be <hi>Eurid, Phyllis, Procris,</hi> and <hi>Creuſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonnets. 13.</head>
               <l>HE that wyll be ſubiect to <hi>Cupidos</hi> call,</l>
               <l>Is chaungd euerie day. I doo not knoe how.</l>
               <l>And of this, I my ſelfe haue made prooues enowe.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Metamorphoſd,</hi> but wot not wherewithall,</l>
               <l>Fyrſt? I was turned to a wandering Harte,</l>
               <l>And ſawe my ſtomacke pierſt with a dolefull arrow.</l>
               <l>Next? Into a Swan, and with a note of ſorrowe.</l>
               <l>I foreſong my death, in <hi>Elegicall</hi> arte.</l>
               <l>Since that, to a Flowre, and ſince withred away:</l>
               <l>Since that, to a Fountaine, and ſince. I am drie:</l>
               <l>And now that <hi>Salamander,</hi> liue in my flame.</l>
               <l>But ye Gods, if euer I haue my owne choyce,</l>
               <l>I wyll be turn'd, into well ſinging voyce:</l>
               <l>And there in louange, the fayre eyes of Ma-dame.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="odes">
            <head>Ode. 2. to his <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg type="strophe">
               <head>Strophe</head>
               <l>AS the little <hi>Meliſſet</hi> flyes,</l>
               <l>(Wanton enfantines of the Skyes)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:11"/>
               <l>With their théeuiſhe pretie tongettes,</l>
               <l>Take the beſt of the fayreſt blomes,</l>
               <l>Maſoning it on their thyettes,</l>
               <l>And therewith build their honny commes.</l>
               <l>Euenſo with a ſprite vigelant,</l>
               <l>I robbe héere, the moſt excellant</l>
               <l>Bloſſomes: in. the garden <hi>Thebêin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And will that through the vniuerce,</l>
               <l>The honny deſtyld in my verce:</l>
               <l>Beare out theſe fayre gréene eies of thine.</l>
               <l>And I will that our <hi>England</hi> ſée,</l>
               <l>By this <hi>Nectar,</hi> that I let fall</l>
               <l>On thee to annoint thee with all,</l>
               <l>What kinde of beauties are in thée.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="antistrophe">
               <head>Antiſtrophe.</head>
               <l>All the ſuperbus frontiſpiſſes,</l>
               <l>And all the threatning ediffices,</l>
               <l>And all the high buildinges are loſt,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Corinthia,</hi> in pride extréeme.</l>
               <l>But that which their Poets did boſt,</l>
               <l>will euer triumph ouer tyme.</l>
               <l>I I golde is <hi>Eliths Palaſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And golde is the Church of <hi>Parnaſſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thoſe that can enter therein,</l>
               <l>Happy are they, and euer ſhall</l>
               <l>Treade on the blacke roofe enfernall,</l>
               <l>Liuing with the enfant <hi>Troyen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That fylles the <hi>Nectar Olympien,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Into the great coope of the God,</l>
               <l>that thondred the menacing head,</l>
               <l>Of the high <hi>Orgullus Phlegren.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:11"/>
               <l>What, what, my too cruell <hi>Diana,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A number haue excelde in <hi>Beautae:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yet it is onelie <hi>Hellina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That lyues: and where in ſaue in <hi>Poiſae.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="epode">
               <head>Epode.</head>
               <l>But thou for whome I writ ſo well:</l>
               <l>And that I wyll make eternell.</l>
               <l>And thou for whome my holie paines,</l>
               <l>Dooth chaſe ignoraunce held ſo long:</l>
               <l>Conioyning in a vulgar ſong:</l>
               <l>The ſecretes, both Gréekes, and Lataines.</l>
               <l>Think'ſt thou it is nothing, to haue</l>
               <l>The penne of <hi>Soothern</hi> for thy trompet.</l>
               <l>Yes, yes, to whome <hi>Soothern</hi> is <hi>Poëte,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The honour goes not to the graue.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iuno,</hi> it's an other thing,</l>
               <l>To heare a well learned voice ſing,</l>
               <l>Or to ſée workes of a wiſe hand:</l>
               <l>Then it's to heare our doting rimors,</l>
               <l>Whoſe labours doo bring both diſhonors,</l>
               <l>To themſelues, and to our <hi>England.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaphs">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:12"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Foure Epytaphes, made by the Countes of <hi>Oxenford,</hi> after the death of her young Sonne, <hi>The Lord Bulbecke, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>HAd with moorning the Gods, left their willes vndon,</l>
               <l>They had not ſo ſoone herited ſuch a ſoule:</l>
               <l>Or if the mouth, tyme dyd not glotton vp all.</l>
               <l>Nor I, nor the world, were depriu'd of my Sonne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breſt <hi>Venus,</hi> with a face dolefull and milde,</l>
               <l>Dooth waſhe with golden teares, inueying the ſkies:</l>
               <l>And when the water of the Goddeſſes eyes,</l>
               <l>Makes almoſt aliue, the Marble, of my Childe:</l>
               <l>One hyds her leaue ſtyll, her dollor ſo extreme,</l>
               <l>Telling her it is not, her young ſonne <hi>Papheme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To which ſhe makes aunſwer with a voice inflamed,</l>
               <l>(Féeling therewith her venime, to be more bitter)</l>
               <l>As I was of <hi>Cupid,</hi> euen ſo of it mother:</l>
               <l>" And a womans laſt chylde, is the moſt beloued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>An other.</head>
               <l>IN dolefull wayes I ſpend the wealth of my time:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Gold, the beſt of all mettelles. Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, the ſweeteſt of all byrdes. And Roſes the faireſt of all flowers.</note>Féeding on my heart, that euer comes agen.</l>
               <l>Since the ordinaunce, of the <hi>Deſtin's,</hi> hath ben,</l>
               <l>To end of the <hi>Saiſſons,</hi> of my yéeres the prime.</l>
               <l>With my So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, my Gold, my Nightingale, and Roſe,</l>
               <l>Is gone: for t'was in him and no other where:</l>
               <l>And well though mine eies run downe like fountaines here,</l>
               <l>The ſtone wil not ſpeak yet, that doth it incloſe.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Deſtins,</hi> and Gods, you might rather haue tanne,</l>
               <l>My twentie yéeres: then the two daies of my ſonne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:12"/>
               <l>And of this world what ſhall I hope, ſince I knoe,</l>
               <l>That in his reſpect, it can yéeld me but moſſe:</l>
               <l>Or what ſhould I conſume any more in woe,</l>
               <l>When Deſtins, Gods, and worlds, are ll in my loſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>An other.</head>
               <l>THe heuens, death, and life? haue coniured my yll:</l>
               <l>For death hath take away the breath of my ſonne:</l>
               <l>The heuens receue, and conſent, that be hath donne:</l>
               <l>And my life dooth kéepe mée heere againſt my will.</l>
               <l>But if our life be cauſ'de with moiſture and heate.</l>
               <l>I care neither for the death, the life, nor ſkyes:</l>
               <l>For I'll ſigh him warmth, and weat him with my eies:</l>
               <l>(And thus I ſhall be thought a ſecond <hi>Promët</hi>)</l>
               <l>And as for life, let it doo me all deſpite:</l>
               <l>For if it leaue me, I ſhall goe to my childe:</l>
               <l>And it in the heuens, there is all my delyght.</l>
               <l>And if I liue, my vertue is immortall.</l>
               <l>" So that the heuens, death and life, when they doo all</l>
               <l>" Their force: by ſorrowfull vertue th'are beguild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>An other.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I Dall,</hi> for <hi>Adon,</hi> neu'r ſhed ſo many teares:</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Thet',</hi> for <hi>Pelid:</hi> nor <hi>Phoebus,</hi> for <hi>Hyacinthus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor for <hi>Atis,</hi> the mother of <hi>Propheteſſes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As for the death of <hi>Bulbecke,</hi> the Gods haue cares.</l>
               <l>At the brute of it, the <hi>Aphroditan</hi> Quéene,</l>
               <l>Cauſed more ſiluer to diſtyll fro her eyes:</l>
               <l>Then when the droppes of her chéekes rayſed Daiſyes:</l>
               <l>And to die with him, mortall, ſhe would haue béene.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Charits,</hi> for it breake their <hi>Peruqs,</hi> of golde:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes,</hi> and the <hi>Nymphes</hi> of Caues: I beholde:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:13"/>
               <l>All the Gods vnder <hi>Olympus</hi> are conſtraint,</l>
               <l>On <hi>Laches, Clothon,</hi> and <hi>Atropos</hi> to plaine.</l>
               <l>And yet beautie, for it dooth make no complaint:</l>
               <l>For it liu'd with him, and died with him againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="variants">
               <head>¶ Others of the fowre laſt lynes, of other that ſhe made alſo.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> My Sonne is gone? and with it, death end my ſorrow,</l>
                  <l n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> But death makes mee aunſwere? Madame, ceaſe theſe mones:</l>
                  <l n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> My force is but on bodies of blood and bones:</l>
                  <l n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> And that of yours, is no more now, but a ſhadow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>An other.</head>
                  <l n="11">
                     <hi>11 Amphiôns</hi> wife was turned to a rocke. O</l>
                  <l n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> How well I had béene, had I had ſuch aduenture,</l>
                  <l n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> For then I might againe haue béene the Sepulcure,</l>
                  <l n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> Of him that I bare in mée, ſo long ago.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:13"/>
            <head>Epitaph, made by the Queenes Maieſtie, at the death of the Princeſſe of <hi>Eſpinoye.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>WHen the warrier <hi>Phoebus,</hi> goth to make his round,</l>
            <l>With a painefull courſe, to too ther <hi>Hemiſphêre:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A darke ſhadowe, a great horror, and a feare,</l>
            <l>In I knoe not what clowdes inueron the ground.</l>
            <l>And euen ſo for <hi>Pinoy,</hi> that fayre vertues Lady,</l>
            <l>(Although <hi>Iupiter</hi> haue in this <hi>Orizôn,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Made a ſtarre of her, by the <hi>Ariadnan</hi> crowne)</l>
            <l>Morns, dolour, and gréefe, accompany our body.</l>
            <l>O <hi>Atropos,</hi> thou haſt doone a worke per-uerſt.</l>
            <l>And as a byrde that hath loſt both young, and neſt:</l>
            <l>About the place where it was, makes many a tourne.</l>
            <l>Euen ſo dooth <hi>Cupid,</hi> that infaunt, God, of amore,</l>
            <l>Flie about the tombe, where ſhe lyes all in dolore,</l>
            <l>Wéeping for her eies, wherein he made ſoiourne.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="selected_extracts">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Verſes taken out of his <hi>Stanſes, Hymnes,</hi> and <hi>Elegias:</hi> all dedicated or ſent to his Miſtreſſe <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Elegia.</head>
               <l>IN which you aſk't my name (confeſſe</l>
               <l>your ſelfe, if't be not ſo)</l>
               <l>And whether I before, had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</l>
               <l>béene in loue or no.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:14"/>
               <l>My name, quoth I, is <hi>Soothern,</hi> and</l>
               <l>Madame, let that ſuffice:</l>
               <l>That <hi>Soothern</hi> which will rayſe the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>language to the Skies.</l>
               <l>The wanton of the <hi>Muſes,</hi> and</l>
               <l>Whoſe well compoſed ryme,</l>
               <l>Will liue in deſpite of the heuens,</l>
               <l>And Triumph ouer tyme. &amp;c.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Elegia.</head>
               <l>But how farre are the wordes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</l>
               <l>to the déedes of men.</l>
               <l>The ſelfe ſame night I went where I</l>
               <l>admyred you agen.</l>
               <l>Your ſyluer <hi>Phebes</hi> eyes, and your</l>
               <l>Well ſet and criſped heair:</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Venus</hi> porte, and your counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce</l>
               <l>of the God of war:</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Iban</hi> throte, your marble brow,</l>
               <l>With your ſoft chéekes of Roſes:</l>
               <l>And your Straberie lyps, wherein</l>
               <l>Your téeth of pearle repoſes.</l>
               <l>Bréefe, I ſaw you <hi>(Dian)</hi> in whome</l>
               <l>The Gods did all their beſt,</l>
               <l>To ſée what they could doo, when they</l>
               <l>Would frame a worke Celeſt. &amp;c.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Elegia.</head>
               <l>But how vaine and ſhort are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes</l>
               <l>and plaſires humaine.</l>
               <l>And of the ſolace of this world:</l>
               <l>What elſe dooth there remaine,</l>
               <l>Sauing but repentaunce: and what</l>
               <l>Is it that beareth breath,</l>
               <l>But by the hauing life, it is</l>
               <l>Subiected vnto death. &amp;c.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb facs="tcp:11450:14"/>
               <head>Himne.</head>
               <l>The more ſtronger the Caſtle is,</l>
               <l>And harder to be wonne,</l>
               <l>The more eternall honour hath,</l>
               <l>The man that can get it.</l>
               <l>And vertue neuer will giue ou'r,</l>
               <l>Without a great conflict. &amp;c.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Himne.</head>
               <l>To iudge a Humaine heart tis a</l>
               <l>Labyrinth, much vnwide,</l>
               <l>Wherein we looſe vs, if we haue</l>
               <l>Not experaunce for guide. &amp;c.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>Elegia.</head>
               <l>The woman nere ſo conſtaunt, or</l>
               <l>the Caſtle nere ſo ſtrong:</l>
               <l>If th'one will heare, and th'other ſpeake,</l>
               <l>They doo not endure long. &amp;c.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="experimental_verse">
            <head>¶ New kinde of verces deuiſed by him: <hi>and are a wofull kinde of meter, to</hi> ſing a loue, or death in.</head>
            <l>LIke the dolefull birde languiſhing,</l>
            <l>the which dooth ſing,</l>
            <l>Her fatall ſong in ſwéete accordes,</l>
            <l>Betaking her ſelfe to her death,</l>
            <l>wearie of breath:</l>
            <l>On <hi>Meander</hi> her ſtorie bordes.</l>
            <l>And euen ſo I, without hope that</l>
            <l>it helpes me ought,</l>
            <l>Bedew thy handes, héere with my teares:</l>
            <l>For I perceiue by thy rigore,</l>
            <l>that-to my dolore:</l>
            <l>The Gods themſelues haue ſtopt their eares.</l>
            <l>Though ſpeake <hi>Dian,</hi> what might thou meane,</l>
            <l>by this extreame.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:15"/>
            <l>Crueltie, hauing ſuch Diuine</l>
            <l>Fayre eyes: Dooſt thou thinke that when death,</l>
            <l>hath tooke my breath:</l>
            <l>That I will ende theſe cries of mine.</l>
            <l>No, no, thou art deceiu'd for then,</l>
            <l>my ſprite agen,</l>
            <l>Shall followe thée fro place to place,</l>
            <l>Exclayming on thy crueltie,</l>
            <l>voide of pittie. &amp;c.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="ode">
            <head>Ode.</head>
            <l>COme, come <hi>Simonid,</hi> and <hi>Anacreon,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Come and laye your money to mine:</l>
            <l>And let vs goe and finde out <hi>Corydon:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And be once dronke with new wine.</l>
            <l>Boye: bring hyther the greateſt glaſſe,</l>
            <l>And fyll, though it runne tyll to morrowe.</l>
            <l>Héere holde my <hi>Anacre-on</hi> quaſſe,</l>
            <l>When we are droonke, we haue no ſorrowe.</l>
            <l>But firſt I would thy <hi>Bathyll</hi> were</l>
            <l>Come with her Lute, that we might daunce.</l>
            <l>And that our olde <hi>Ronſard</hi> of <hi>Fraunce,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With his <hi>Caſſandra</hi> too were here.</l>
            <l>And what ſayſt <hi>Simon'd</hi> ſhall we ſend,</l>
            <l>For our Wenches, now at beginning:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hâ,</hi> he that loues not Wine, and Women,</l>
            <l>Will neuer make a holſome ende.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="odellet">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:15"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Odellet.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>DIan,</hi> if it might come to paſſe:</l>
            <l>Or that I might haue my deſire:</l>
            <l>I would to the Gods that I were,</l>
            <l>Turned into thy looking Glaſſe.</l>
            <l>Or to the pillowe of this bead:</l>
            <l>Whereon thou layſt thy daintie head.</l>
            <l>Or to water, that I might waſh thée:</l>
            <l>Or to thy roabe, that thou mightſt weare mée:</l>
            <l>Or that hang here on thy teatine,</l>
            <l>I would I were theſe pearles of thine.</l>
            <l>Or my <hi>Dian,</hi> to tell thée true,</l>
            <l>I would I could be but thy ſhew.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="odellet">
            <head>Odellet.</head>
            <l>SOme will ſing the great feates of Armes</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Rome:</hi> ſome other the alarmes</l>
            <l>of <hi>Thebs:</hi> and ſome other of <hi>Troye,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And both the ſiedge, and the efroye.</l>
            <l>But what haue I to doe with warriers:</l>
            <l>Meddle I then with thoſe that fit:</l>
            <l>No, no, I nere hurt any yet:</l>
            <l>Nor nere men to come among ſoldiers.</l>
            <l>I care not for the <hi>Thracian</hi> God:</l>
            <l>I am no man that ſeeketh blood:</l>
            <l>But like the olde <hi>Poët Annacron,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It pleaſes mée well to be <hi>Biberon.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And thus in a Sellor to quaffe,</l>
            <l>So that ſome Wench be by to lauffe.</l>
            <l>And with <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and <hi>Citherais,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I meane to ſpend all my whole dayes.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="odellet">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:16"/>
            <head>Odellet.</head>
            <l>BOy: reach hyther the bottle, that</l>
            <l>I may taſte of thy crimſon lycor:</l>
            <l>For when I am in any dolor,</l>
            <l>It onelie reioyces my heart.</l>
            <l>The deuill made money I thinke:</l>
            <l>For without money, what a liuing,</l>
            <l>Haue we that ſerue couetous women:</l>
            <l>And without it we can not drinke.</l>
            <l>Learning is not now woorth a penny,</l>
            <l>And theſe wiues care for no fayre lookes,</l>
            <l>And what ſhall a man doo with Bookes.</l>
            <l>Faith hang, if he can get no mony.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="odellet">
            <head>Odellet.</head>
            <l>BVt why ſince, death will not retard,</l>
            <l>For any gift that we her offer:</l>
            <l>My <hi>Dyolle,</hi> what helpes it to gard,</l>
            <l>This golde, a rouſting in a coffer.</l>
            <l>Is't not better that whiles we liue,</l>
            <l>We giue our ſelues to learning: when</l>
            <l>Better then ought elſe we can giue,</l>
            <l>(Dead) it makes vs to reuiue agen.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="stansse">
            <pb facs="tcp:11450:16"/>
            <head>Stanſſe.</head>
            <l>DIeus que ie hay (ronſard) qui rien neſe propoze,</l>
            <l>Qu'a tromper vne amour d'un la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage allechant,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dian</hi> ie vos pry aiez loreille e cloze,</l>
            <l>Affin de n'ouyr point la doulceur de ſon chant.</l>
            <l>Non ie hay plus que mort ſa Caſandre implacable,</l>
            <l>An caeur ou le Burin d'une douce Pitye,</l>
            <l>Ne ſeut grauer benin vn ſeull trait d'amytie,</l>
            <l>" Car on doibt payer l'amour d'une amitye ſemblable.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="quadran">
            <head>Quadran.</head>
            <l>Lon ne peut inger leſant dans le viſage,</l>
            <l>Sy l'amant eſt fidelle, ou volage, en amoure:</l>
            <l>Pour le ſcau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir an vray fueilletez le Courage,</l>
            <l>" Car la durable amytye ne ſe'preuue en vn ioure.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="quadran">
            <head>Quadran.</head>
            <l>Non non, Ie ne tiens point pour guerrier valeureux,</l>
            <l>Vng tas de ieunes ſots qui ventant leur Vaillance,</l>
            <l>" Au fruit on congnoiſt larbre: a la perſeuerance,</l>
            <l>" Lon remarque anſsi tost vn gallant amoureus.</l>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
